

Daria V. Diachkova

Senior Frontend Engineer and small team Frontend Lead

GitHub: dariadia
Website: portfolio

ABOUT ME

UX and inclusivity-focused Senior Frontend Engineer and small team Frontend Lead (≤5 team members) with 5+ years of experience in React, Node.js and TypeScript.

My **communication** skills allow me to efficiently collaborate with development & design teams and take on **mentoring** duties.

Current commit count: ≈ 7K.

SPECIALIZATIONS

- ♦ Web Content Accessibility Guidelines (WCAG)
- Front-End Development (React.js, JavaScript, TypeScript)
- ◆ Team Management & Mentoring
- ◆ Agile (scrum) development

I SPEAK

English and Russian (Native) German (Proficient) (Elementary) Serbian (Fluent) Japanese

CONTACT INFO:

Email: <u>dariavdiachkova@gmail.com</u> Telephone: +381 621254648 Telegram: <u>@redheadalert</u> LinkedIn: <u>dariadiachkova</u>

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

SENIOR FRONTEND ENGINEER AND TEAM FRONTEND LEAD Bookmate, Ireland | August 2022 - now

- Team management: provide leadership and mentorship to the frontend development team. Foster a collaborative and inclusive team culture and encourage professional growth. Set goals and provide regular feedback to team members.
- Technical expertise: bring my strong frontend development skills to the team, serving
 as a technical advisor and providing guidance on complex technical challenges while
 partaking in daily tasks as the "player-coach"
- Project planning and coordination: collaborate with project managers and stakeholders to plan and prioritize frontend development tasks. Break down projects into manageable tasks and allocate resources effectively. Ensure that timelines are met and deliverables are of high quality.
- Collaboration with other teams: work closely with backend developers, UI/UX
 designers and other cross-functional teams to ensure seamless integration. Foster
 effective communication and collaboration to align the frontend development efforts
 with overall project goals.

Some stats

- Raised and mentored: 1 intern and 3 junior developers.
- Introduced WCAG principles (accessibility for all);
- Improved <u>bookmate.com</u> loading time by **153%**. Chunks refactoring, a combination of async/defer fetching and improved runtime for better UX.
- Launched two major game-changing features for the product: a new async purchase mechanism and an option to pay via Apple/Google Pay. (Before users could only manually enter their card details)
- Launched the "Year In Review" project: a new interactive website section with
 personalised user statistics, graphs on their reading habits, as well as general maps
 with data collected from around the world.
- Implemented the frontend coding part and launched Bookmate x Partner integrations with: Yettel (Hungary), MTN (Ghana).

SENIOR FRONTEND DEVELOPER

Bookmate, Ireland | January 2022 - August 2022

- Collaboration and communication: communicate effectively with team members and stakeholders, seeking clarification when needed and providing updates on progress and challenges. Actively contribute to team discussions and brainstorming sessions.
- Problem-solving: Demonstrate problem-solving skills by identifying and resolving technical challenges encountered during development. Analyze issues, propose solutions and implement fixes to ensure the smooth functioning of the application.

Some stats

- Upped bookmate.com test coverage from 31% to 56%;
- Improved <u>bookmate.com</u> loading time from score 27% to score 68%. Lessened API strain, improved SEO;

MIDDLE FRONTEND DEVELOPER

Bookmate, Ireland | February 2021 - January 2022

- User experience: collaborate with designers to create user-friendly and intuitive interfaces.
- Testing and debugging: perform testing and debugging to identify and resolve issues, ensuring a bug-free and reliable UX. Utilize debugging tools to troubleshoot and optimize code.
- **Documentation and version control**: maintain documentation of features and technical specifications. Utilize version control systems (**git**) to manage repositories, branches and code reviews effectively.

Some stats

- Upped internal projects' test coverage by 15%.
- Introduced technical documentation to the frontend team. Covered 60% of the main product (website).

ACADEMIC BACKGROUND

WEB DEVELOPMENT

Geekbrains University (Mail Group) | 2018-2020

- Graduated in the top 10% of my class
- Skills acquired: Frontend Development · React.js
 JavaScript · Responsive Web Design · Git ·
 Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) · HTML5 · Node.js ·
 Sass · MySQL

BACHELOR OF WORLD ECONOMICS AND WORLD POLITICS

Higher School of Economics | 2015-2019

• Graduated with a GPA of 9.7 (out of 10)

CERTIFICATES

- <u>Front End Development Libraries</u> (August 2023) #React.JS
- <u>JavaScript Algorithms and Data Structures</u>
 (February 2022) #JavaScript #algorithms
- Responsive Web Design (June 2021) #HTML5
 #Git #Responsive Web Design
- Architectures and Design Patterns (March 2020)
- DataBase MySql (December 2019)
- HTML&CSS. Advanced level (February 2019)
 #HTML #CSS

JUNIOR FRONTEND DEVELOPER

Bookmate, Ireland | February 2020 - February 2021

- Implement designs: from design mockups to web pages using HTML, CSS and JavaScript. Ensure that the design is accurately translated into code while maintaining responsiveness and cross-browser compatibility.
- Manage changes to source code using git.

Some stats

- Boosted <u>Bookmate Zurnal</u> (website) performance by 82% (better UX, faster page load, less API strain);
- Improved a corporate internal app's UX (CDN uploader) to make it intuitive to use.

MY PROJECTS

- ◆ Year In Review: a multilanguage landing page on reading statics of an e-library service. Includes an interactive map and graphs.
- ◆ <u>Design System</u>: an npm package. This is a modular component library and gives you building blocks for your own React applications.
- ◆ <u>Kanban board</u>: in this app, one can add, edit, delete tasks and columns, and drag and drop tasks between the columns.
- ♦ More in my portfolio

PASSION PROJECTS

- ◆ <u>The Algorithm Series</u>: my technical blog, where I explain how to solve algorithm tasks (from Leetcode).
- ◆ <u>Geister (RPG)</u>: an RPG game about ghost-adventures in an old library. Runs on JS and canvas technologies.

RECOMMENDATIONS



Olga Alexeeva

Product & Program Manager | Product Leader, Certified Agile Professional | 12+ years in building digital products | Data-driven, tech background

If you wish to find a Frontend Lead more dependable and knowledgeable than a full-fledged CTO, look no further. In Bookmate, I'm constantly relying on her vast product experience and her unbelievable abilities to deliver almost any task in a blink of an eye. Getting things implemented, experimenting and having fun while working together has never been easier.

Every stakeholder adores Daria's gentle and positive approach to most difficult projects, and we are all spoiled beyond reason by having her in the team. I'd definitely recommend considering her in many roles, starting from an experienced developer and up to a team leader with outstanding mentoring capabilities.



Tatsiana Kulikova QA Engineer

For over a year, I worked as a QA engineer with Daria, the amazing lead frontend developer at Bookmate. Seriously, this person is a rock star! What I admire most of all is how much Daria loves frontend development. For her, it's not just a job - it's a passion. You can see it in every line of code she writes and in every pixel on the screen.

Daria is also a team player. She is always ready for feedback and to brainstorm solutions together with the team. She is also always ready to help and explain complicated technical issues in simple words. Communicating with her is fun and easy, both about work stuff and about life.

If you are looking for someone who not only has the necessary skills but is also genuinely passionate about her work, Daria is the right person for you.